<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<preface id="about" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>About this guide</title>
  <para>This guide is intended to serve users of the Distributed
    Replicated Block Device (DRBD) as a definitive reference guide and
    handbook.</para>
  <para>It is being made available to the DRBD community by <ulink
      url="http://www.linbit.com/">LINBIT</ulink>, the project's
    sponsor company, free of charge and in the hope that it will be
    useful. The guide is continuously being updated; we (the authors)
    try to add information about new DRBD features simultaneously with
    the corresponding DRBD releases. An on-line HTML version of this
    guide is always available at <ulink
      url="http://www.drbd.org/users-guide/"/>.</para>
  <para>This guide is organized in five parts and one appendix:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para><xref linkend="p-intro"/> deals with DRBD's basic
	functionality. It gives a short overview of
	DRBD's positioning within the Linux I/O stack, and about
	fundamental DRBD concepts. It also examines DRBD's most
	important features in detail.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para><xref linkend="p-build-install-configure"/> talks about
	building DRBD from source, installing pre-built DRBD packages,
	and contains an overview of getting DRBD running on a cluster
	system.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para><xref linkend="p-work"/> is about managing DRBD,
	configuring and reconfiguring DRBD resources, and common
	troubleshooting scenarios.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para><xref linkend="p-apps"/> deals with leveraging DRBD to
	  add storage replication and high availability to
	  applications. It not only covers DRBD integration in the
	  Pacemaker cluster manager, but also advanced LVM
	  configurations, integration of DRBD with GFS, and adding
	  high availability to Xen virtualization environments.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para><xref linkend="p-learn"/> dives into DRBD's internals,
	  and also contains pointers to other resources which readers
	  of this guide may find useful.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Finally, <xref linkend="ap-man-pages"/> contains online
	versions of the Linux manual pages distributed with the latest
	DRBD version, for reference purposes.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>Individual sections of this guide may be marked as
    <quote>Draft</quote>, such sections have been recently added and
    should not be considered authoritative.</para>
  <para>An extended version of this guide is available to customers of
    LINBIT. Access to the extended version is included in LINBIT's
    support and training services. The extended version contains
    information on the following topics, not included in this version
    of the guide:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>DRBD performance tuning and optimization,</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>creating and administering three-node replication
	  configurations,</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>creating and administering configurations optimized for
	  narrow-bandwith WAN replication,</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>various <quote>hints and kinks</quote> for advanced DRBD
	users.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>Users interested in DRBD training or support services are
    asked to contact <email>sales@linbit.com</email>.</para>
  <para>This guide was generated from its original sources on
    <xi:include href="builddate" parse="text"/>.</para>
</preface>
